Guide to the Marcia M. Mathews papers and photographs, 1833-1976, bulk 1939-1976 RL.11884
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Marcia M. Mathews papers and photographs
1833-1976
1939-1976
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Mathews, Marcia M.
Fenton family (Rochdale, England)
RL.11884
3.0 Linear Feet 4 boxes; 1 oversize folder
Marcia M. Mathews (1904-1990) was an art historian and author residing in Durham, North Carolina. Collection comprises materials relating to two research projects conducted by Mathews: one on Roger Fenton, lawyer and early English photographer; and a later project on African American sculptor Richmond Barthé. The Fenton series includes letters (1940s-1950s) from Fenton descendants, many of which comment on the aftermath of the war; images of the family home, Crimble Hall in Rochdale, England; photographs of Fenton and his family (1860s); and modern copies of his own photographs (1850s). The Barthé papers consist of a draft biography by Mathews, and 134 photographs of his sculptures and other artwork, as well as early portraits of Barthé and his family, and were acquired by the John Hope Franklin Research Center for African and African American History and Culture. Although Barthé had relationships with men over his lifetime, the biography appears to make no overt mention of his sexuality. The collection also includes a large scrapbook for the year 1939 containing U.S. news stories and articles about the war and on Fascism in the U.S.
Arrangement
The Barthé photographs are arranged in three groups: portraits of Barthé and his family; photographs of his artwork; and several photographs of exhibits or installations.
Biographical Note
Marcia M. Mathews (1904-1990) was a Georgia-born art historian and author who resided in Atlanta, Georgia, and in Durham, N.C. until her death. She taught art history at Duke in the 1930s, and was married to Joseph James Mathews, European history professor whose papers are also in the Duke collections. In addition to her research on Roger Fenton, she wrote articles and monographs on African American artists, including Henry Ossawa Tanner and Marian Anderson; her biography of artist Richmond Barthé is unpublished.
Roger Fenton (1819-1869) was born in Lancashire, Rochdale Borough, and resided at his family's ancestral home, Crimble Hall. He studied law and art, then in the 1850s turned to photography, experimenting with the wet collodion process, then in its infancy. He took many photographs of the Crimean War, thus becoming one of the world's first war photographers. Fenton was a founder of the Royal Photographic Society and its first honorary secretary. Queen Victoria was one of his patrons: he photographed her family and attended royal audiences where he described his experiences in the Crimea.
Richmond Barthé, or James Richmond Barthé, was born in Mississippi in 1901, and died in Pasadena, California in 1989. After studying at the Art Institute of Chicago, he went on to become a sculptor; he also painted. Barthé had several relationships with men during his lifetime. He resided in several places through his career: New York City; Jamaica, where he bought a home; Florence, Italy; and then Southern California. At a time when African American artists were underrepresented in American academies and galleries, he won many awards and became one of the first African American artists to be represented in the Metropolitan Museum of Art's permanent collections.
[Source: adapted from typescript biography in collection and Wikipedia, viewed February 2021]
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Marcia M. Mathews papers and photographs were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1976 and 2020.
Related Materials
href="https://archives.lib.duke.edu/catalog/mathewsjosephjames">Joseph James Mathews papers, 1833-1976
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Content Description
The papers of author and art historian Marcia M. Mathews comprise materials chiefly relating to two research projects: Mathew's search for material on Roger Fenton, a mid-19th century lawyer and early photographer; and an unpublished typescript and photographs relating to her research on African American sculptor Richmond Barthé. Other materials include a large war scrapbook for the year 1939 with many articles and clippings about Fascism in the U.S., and a biographical sketch of her career.
The Roger Fenton series consists chiefly of Mathews' research materials and sketches relating to Fenton, and correspondence (1940s-1950s) between Mathews and Fenton descendants. The series concludes with a group of a dozen photographs, including cartes-de-visite of his family and 20th century copies of Roger Fenton's 1850s photographs of the Crimean War, the south front of the Kremlin, three of Queen Victoria's children, and a landscape with a bridge. There is also a photograph and a photo of a sketch of Crimble Hall, the family seat in Rochdale, England.
Materials on Richmond Barthé consist of Marcia Mathews' unpublished typescript draft biography (circa 1975), covering Barthé's entire life and career up to age 75. Although he was known to have had a number of relationships with men over his lifetime, the biography appears to make no overt mention of his sexuality.
The 134 photographs in the Barthé series are chiefly black-and-white images of his most important sculptures and other artwork, with several early family portraits of Barthé, his mother, and stepfather (circa 1915, 1935, and circa 1940). Subjects of the sculptures are most frequently Black figure studies, including African characters; busts of well-known African Americans such as Booker T. Washington, Jimmie Daniels, Josephine Baker, and others; religious themes; and race-related themes, expressed in such works as "The awakening of Africa," "The wounded slave," and "Mother with lynched son," with its direct reference to Michelangelo's Pietà. He also lived in Jamaica and completed a number of Jamaican government commissions for statues of national heroes, coinage, and medallions. The Barthé papers were acquired by the John Hope Franklin Research Center for African and African American History and Culture.
African American artists -- Biography; African American sculptors -- United States -- 20th century -- Biography; African American sculpture -- United States -- 20th century; African Americans in art; Art, Jamaican -- 20th century; Gay artists -- United States; Photographers -- England -- 19th century; Photography -- England -- History -- 19th century; Sculptors -- United States -- 20th century -- Biography; World War, 1939-1945 -- England -- Personal narratives, English; World War, 1939-1945 -- United States -- Press coverage; Sculpture -- United States -- 20th century; Harlem (New York, N.Y.) -- Social life and customs -- 20th century; Jamaica -- Intellectual life; New York (N.Y.) -- Intellectual life; New York (N.Y.) -- Social conditions; Rochdale (England) -- History; Black-and-white photographs; Cartes-de-visite photographs (card photographs); Gelatin silver prints; Scrapbooks; Sculpture (visual work); Typescripts; Barthé, Richmond, 1901-1989; Fenton, Roger, 1819-1869
- Roger Fenton research papers and photographs, 1833-1976; 1.5 Linear Feet 2 boxes; 1 oversize folder
  Scope and Contents
  The series includes research materials assembled by art historian Marcia M. Mathews on early English photographer Roger Fenton. The earliest date reflects a transcript of a letter from 1833 from Roger to his mother while he was at school.
  Mathews does not appear to have published any work based on this research, and there are no drafts in the collection, although she seems to have been involved at some level in Helmut Gernsheim's book on Fenton, published in London in 1954. The dozens of letters to Mathews from Fenton family members (1940s-1957) mention this connection and may shed more light on it.
  Other correspondence is from curators at various institutions where Fenton's photographs and papers were located, and from the photography lab where professional copies were made of his original photographs taken in the 1850s.
  Included in the series are six 2 1/2 x 4" cartes-de-visite photographs of Roger Fenton and his family (wife and daughters), early 1860s. Other photographs are copies (circa 1940s) and include images of the Fenton home, Crimble Hall (Rochdale Borough, Lancashire, England), and of other family members. There appears to be an original unmounted albumen print of a full standing portrait, probably by Fenton, of his father-in-law (last name Maynard), as well as several copies of photographs by Roger Fenton (1850s). One modern copy photograph is of a sketch of Crimble Hall by Marcia Mathews.
  Other items include a copy of a questionnaire about the Fenton family, created by Mathews in the 1940s and sent to various Fenton relatives; it is accompanied by one respondent's handwritten answers.
  - Research materials on Roger Fenton and questionnaire, 1940s (Box 1)
  - Correspondence with Fenton family members and others, 1833, 1940s-1957 and undated; 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Photographs of Roger Fenton, Fenton family, and others, approximately 1850s-1860s; 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Copy photographs of Fenton's photographs, and Marcia Mathews' sketch of Crimble Hall, 1940s (Box 1)
  - Oversize photographs (Oversize-folder Oversize MSS Box Run A:3 Folder 1)
- Marcia M. Mathews biographical sketch and World War II scrapbook, 1939, 1976
  - Biographical sketch by and about Marcia M. Mathews (typescript), 1976 (Box 1)
  - Scrapbook of newspapers and clippings, 1939 (Box 2)
    This large scrapbook contains articles and newspapers from one year, 1939, that deal almost exclusively with the war in Spain, Fascism, and the war in Europe and the Pacific. There are multiple features on Fascism in the United States, including journalistic accounts of violence against Jews and others, and articles attempting to educate the public about Fascism in the U.S., with examples of American Fascist propaganda. There is no associated name evident in the volume, but it may have been assembled by Marcia Mathews.
- Richmond Barthé unpublished biography and photographs, circa 1915-circa 1975
  The series chiefly consists of a 137-page draft biography on African American sculptor Richmond Barthé, in typescript form, completed by art historian Marcia M. Mathews sometime around 1975, accompanied by 134 photographs of Barthé's sculptures, as well as a few family portraits.
  The highly-researched biography covers the life and career of Barthé, from his birth in Mississippi in 1901 to his age at the time the draft was completed, 75 years, thus the estimated date of 1975 for the draft's completion. Appended are footnotes and a bibliography. The work offers many insights on Barthé's career and struggles as an African American artist; it also offers details about the community of friends who supported him, which included many gay artists and theater people. Although the work was unpublished as a monograph, Mathews wrote an article about Barthé in the South Atlantic Quarterly (#74, 1975) entitled Richmond Barthé, sculptor..
  The rest of the series comprises 134 professional glossy photographs of Barthé's sculptures and a few paintings, almost all 8x10 inch gelatin silver prints. They typically include a title for the work penciled in on the verso in an unknown hand; less commonly, they include a date, probably of the work's completion, and occasionally, a photographer's name; in twelve photos the name is that of Eric Pollitzer of Hempstead, N.Y.
  There are also color snapshots of Barthé in Florence, 1971, of what appears to be an early solo exhibit (1930s?), as well as early portraits of Barthé (1915, 1935), his mother, and stepfather.
  Subjects for the sculptures are almost always Black figure studies such as males and female nudes, dancers, athletes, family groups, and busts; others are of commissioned sculptures of Black authors, inventors, celebrities, and other figures. There are also race-related themes and religious sculptures (Barthé was a practicing Catholic).
  - Photographs of Richmond Barthé and family members, circa 1915, 1930s, circa 1940, and 1971; 2 folders 6 photographs (Box 3)
    Includes 1971-era color snapshot of Barthé in Florence, and early portraits of Barthé (1915, 1935), his mother (1930s?), and stepfather (1940s?).
  - Photographs of Barthé sculptures (small prints), 22 photographs (Box 3)
  - Photographs of Barthé coins and medallions, 6 photographs (Box 3)
  - Typescript draft of unpublished biography of sculptor Richmond Barthé by Marcia M. Mathews, circa 1975 (Box 3)
  - Photographs of installations of Barthé's sculptures, 6 photographs (Box 4)
    The two large black-and-white 8x10 inch prints appear to be from a fairly early show, perhaps 1930s, while the color snapshots seem to indicate a private home setting, perhaps Barthé's apartment in Florence.
  - Photographs of Richmond Barthé sculptures and other artwork, 98 photographs chiefly 8x10 inch prints (Box 4)